# Chirag Gupta, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Associate Waisman Center, University of Wisconsin Madison, Wisconsin, USA Webpage: cngupta.github.io Email: cngupta@protonmail.com





#### SUMMARY

Bioinformatics Scientist with 4+ years of postdoctoral experience in research and analysis of genomics data. I am interested in developing computational approaches to glean actionable insights from large-scale multi-omics data. I am currently working on building machine learning models to guide biomarker discovery and assist in clinical decision making. I have extensive experience in written and oral communication to academics and business leaders through contributions to winning grants, 12+ peer reviewed publications, and several conference appearances.

#### **EDUCATION**

2017	Ph.D. Computational Biology (Cell and Molecular Biology) Dissertation: Transcriptome-based gene networks for systems-level analysis of gene function	<b>University of Arkansas,</b> Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2009 2007	M.S. Bioinformatics B.S. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India Sardar Patel University, India

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2021 – present	<ul> <li>Postdoctoral Research Associate</li> <li>Single cell genomics of the human brain</li> <li>Cell type network biology</li> <li>Network-based drug discovery</li> </ul>	University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, USA
2017 – 2020	<ul> <li>Postdoctoral Research Associate</li> <li>Plant and crop genomics</li> <li>Gene prioritization protocols</li> <li>Web-applications for biologists</li> </ul>	University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2012 – 2017	<ul> <li>Graduate Research Assistant</li> <li>Plant stress and developmental biology</li> <li>Large-scale transcriptomics</li> <li>Gene regulatory networks</li> </ul>	University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2008 — 2009	<ul> <li>Student Researcher</li> <li>Fusion proteins in cancer</li> <li>Protein structure prediction</li> <li>Molecular modeling, drug designing</li> </ul>	<b>Disha Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd.</b> , Gujarat, India

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Under review/preprints

- 1. **Chirag Gupta**, Jielin Xu, Ting Jin, Saniya Khullar, Xiaoyu Liu, Sayali Alatkar, Feixiong Cheng, Daifeng Wang. Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease. (*preprint*)
- 2. **Chirag Gupta**, Arjun Krishnan, Andrew Schneider, Cynthia Denbow, Eva Collakova, Pawel Wolinski, Andy Pereira. SANe: The Seed Active Network for Discovering Transcriptional Regulatory Programs of Seed Development. (*preprint*)

# Peer reviewed journal articles

- Chirag Gupta, Pramod Chandrashekar, Chenfeng He, Ting Jin, Saniya Khullar, Qiang Chang, Daifeng Wang. Bringing machine learning to research on intellectual and developmental disabilities: taking inspiration from neurological diseases. in press, *Journal of Neurodevelopmental Disorders* (IDDRC 2022 special issue on computational neuroscience), *May 2022*. [full text]
- 2. Anuj Kumar, **Chirag Gupta**, Julie Thomas, Andy Pereira. Genetic Dissection of Grain Yield Component Traits Under High Nighttime Temperature Stress in a Rice Diversity Panel. **Frontiers in Plant Science**, September 2021. [full text]
- 3. **Chirag Gupta**, Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Andy Pereira. Using network-based machine learning to predict transcription factors involved in drought stress resistance. *Frontiers in Genetics*, *June 2021.* [full text]
- 4. Raksha Singh, Rohana Liyanage, **Chirag Gupta**, Jackson Lay Jr., Andy Pereira, Clemencia Rojas. The protein interactomes of AtNHR2A and AtNHR2B unraveled common and specialized functions in plant immunity integrating distinct biological processes. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, *March 2020. [full text]*
- 5. Min Woo Lee, Carmen S. Padilla, **Chirag Gupta**, Aravind Galla, Andy Pereira, Jiamei Li, Fiona L. Goggin. The FATTY ACID DESATURASE 2 family in tomato contributes to primary metabolism and stress responses. *Plant Physiology*, *Nov. 2019.* [full text]
- 6. **Chirag Gupta** and Andy Pereira. Recent advances in gene function prediction using context-specific coexpression networks in plants. *F1000Research*, Feb. 2019. [full text]
- 7. Arjun Krishnan, **Chirag Gupta**, Madana MR Ambavaram, Andy Pereira. RECoN: Rice Environment Co-expression Network for systems level analysis of abiotic-stress response. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, Sep. 2017. [full text]
- 8. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Upinder Singh Gill, Palaiyur Nanjappan Sivalingam, Aarti Gupta, **Chirag Gupta**, Geetha Govind, Karaba N Nataraja, Andy Pereira, Makarla Udayakumar, Kirankumar S Mysore, Muthappa Senthil-Kumar. GBF3 transcription factor imparts drought tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana. *Scientific Reports*, *August 2017.* [full text]

 Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Chirag Gupta, Andy Pereira. Regulation of grain yield in rice under well-watered and drought stress conditions by GUDK. Plant Signaling and Behavior, January 2015. [full text]

# **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

# Talks

- Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimer's Association International Conference, San Diego, CA, 2<sup>nd</sup> August 2022
- Predicting rice genes important for drought tolerance using gene regulatory networks and machine learning. Crops InSilico, 4th Annual Symposium and Hackathon, Urbana, IL, 3<sup>rd</sup> May 2019
- Arabidopsis seed-filling association-network analysis. American Society of Plant Biologists – Southern Section (ASPB-SS), Lexington, KY, 30<sup>th</sup> March 2014.

#### Select posters

- Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease, Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, Madison, WI, July 2022
- Network analysis of human brain cell types under Alzheimer's disease and healthy conditions, Society of Neuroscience, Chicago, IL, November 2021
- Network-based approach to prioritize lung cancer genes from whole-exome sequencing data. Arkansas Bioinformatics Consortium, Little Rock, AR, 25th March 2018
- [Award winning poster] An abiotic-stress conditioned gene regulatory network in rice predicted using an ensemble of reverse-engineering solutions. The 25th Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) Conference, San Diego, CA, 14th January 2017
- A resource for systems analysis of stress response in rice. NSF Workshop on plant development and drought stress, Monterey, CA, 8th November 2015
- In Silico Analysis of Fusion Proteins in Cancer, International Conference on Biomedical and Genomic Research, Ahmedabad, India, 30th January 2009

## **A**WARDS

- 1. Crops in silico underrepresented minority travel scholarship, **Crops InSilico**, Urbana, IL, 2019
- 2. Scherago International Student Travel Grants Awards, **The 25th annual Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) meeting**, San Diego, CA, 2017
- 3. NSF Travel Grant to attend the Workshop on Plant Development and Drought Stress, **National Science Foundation**, 2015
- 4. Stood 3rd in merit list for all India entrance examination for Master's in bioinformatics program, **Sardar Patel University**, India, 2007
- 5. 2nd Prize in undergraduate oral presentation, Sardar Patel University, India, 2006
- 6. 3rd Prize in undergraduate poster competition, Atmiya University, India, 2006

#### **GRANT CONTRIBUTIONS**

 NSF EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC 1826836: Systems genetics studies on rice genomes for analysis of grain yield and quality under heat stress (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$4,659,406), 2018 • **NSF MCB 1716844**: Systems genetics analysis of photosynthetic carbon metabolism in rice (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$798,725.00), 2017

## **SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS**

2019 - present
2022 - present
The International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB)
The Alzheimer's Association International Society to Advance

Alzheimer's Research and Treatment (ISTAART)

SELECT SKILLS

Programming R, Python, Perl, PHP, mySQL

Bioinformatics Raw sequence data (NGS) processing, quality control, and downstream

analysis (single-cell, bulk); differential gene expression, variant calling, gene-

set enrichment analysis, network analysis

Data science Machine learning (data cleaning, feature extraction, model training and

evaluation); Supervised and unsupervised learning

Visualization R, Shiny, Cytoscape

Platforms Docker; Linux, MacOS; Google Cloud

### **TOOLS DEVELOPED**

GRAiN http://rrn.uark.edu/shiny/apps/GRAiN/
SANe https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/SANe/
RECoN https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/RECoN/

# **MENTORING EXEPRIENCE**

Mentored a graduate student (Masters in Statistics, UW) and four undergraduate students under the University of Madison's Undergraduate Research Scholar contract for two semesters, 2021-2022. Project title: "Using network-based machine Learning to predict genes underlying neurological disorders"

## **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

Co-taught Plant Genomics (**Bioinformatics/Genomics modules**: CSES 5543, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2016, 2018

#### **EXTENSION ACTIVITIES**

Student and Teacher Workshop: rice genetic variation (18 credit hours, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2019

# ACADEMIC SERVICE

- Manuscript reviewer for Human Molecular Genetics, Journal of Neurodevelopmental Disorders, Plant Physiology, Frontiers in Plant Science, Nature Scientific Reports, Rice, Plant Cell Reports, Horticultural Plant Journal, Plant Methods, PLoS One, iMETA.
- Plante Fellow 2019: Contribution to the Plantae online portal for Bioinformatics resources relevant to plant biology research

- **Member of the panel of judges** for the Northwest Arkansas Regional Science and Engineering Fair 2015,16
- Conducted several training material and hands-on activities for undergraduates and K-12 students from the Arkansas agricultural areas in the Delta region for a STEM literacy outreach program

# **R**EFREES

Available upon request